<sect1 id="toolbars_menus_functions">
		<title>Functions in menu and toolbars</title>
		<para>
				Following functions are called from menu and toolbars and provide
				user friendly enviroment for simple editing.
		</para>

		<sect2 id="gui_onclickFunctions_selectionModes" xreflabel="selection modes">
				<title>Selection modes</title>
				<para>
						Modes in this section can be used to select objects on the
						displayed page. All modes support move and resize of selected objects, 
						but the real functionality depends on implemented scripts, which perform
						real action with selected objects (e.g. moving nongraphical
						operators (text, pictures) and moving annotation activation rectangle,
						but moving graphical operators (line, rectangle, ...) is not implemented).
				</para>
				<para>
						When moving selected objects cursor must be in the selected
						region (cursor pointer will change to cross from arrows pointer). After pressing 
						the mouse left button selection region
						can be moved. After releasing mouse left button script moving function is executed
						on the selected operators.
				</para>
				<para>
						When resizing objects cursor must be moved to the edge of bounding
						rectangle of selected region (cursor will change to two arrow oriented from each
						other direction - there are four possibilities how to resize: left-right, top-bottom,
						(left-top)-(right-bottom) and (left-bottom)-(right-top)). After pressing the left
						mouse button selected region is resized by cursor movement. Script function for
						resizing is executed when mouse left button is released.
				</para>
				<para>
						When cancelling started action press <emphasis>Esc</emphasis> key before releasing left mouse
						button. 
						If <emphasis>Esc</emphasis> key is pressed during no action all objects
						on the page are unselected.
				</para>
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectAll;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectGraphicalOp;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectText;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectAnnotations;
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="drawing_adding_new">
				<title>Drawing and adding new objects</title>
				&gui_onclickFunctions_drawLine;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_drawRect;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_addText;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_strikeThrough;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_highlightingText;
		</sect2>
</sect1>
