<sect1>
		<title>Functions in menu and toolbars</title>
		<para>
				Following functions are calling from menu and toolbars and provide
				user friendly enviroments for simple editing pdf documents.
		</para>

		<sect2>
				<title>Selection modes</title>
				<para>
						Modes in this section are using to selecting objects on
						viewed page. Inside all this modes is implemented possibility
						move and resize selected objects, but this functionalities are
						dependence on implemented scripts, which do concrete actions with
						selected objects (e.g. is implemented scripts for moving nongraphical
						operators (text, pictures) and moving annotation's activation rectangle,
						but is not implemented moving graphical operators (line, rectangle, ...)
						and resizing functions for all operators and annotations).
				</para>
				<para>
						If user wish move selected objects, then must move mouse cursor into
						selected region (cursor will change to 4 arrow starting in 1 middle
						point - cross from arrows). After press left button, selection region
						is moving by movement of cursor. Script function for moving is execute
						on release mouse left button.
				</para>
				<para>
						If user wish resize objects, then must move mouse cursor on edge of bounding
						rectangle of selected region (cursor will change to 2 arrow oriented from each
						other direct in allowed resizing way - are 4 possibilities: left-right, top-bottom,
						(left-top)-(right-bottom) and (left-bottom)-(right-top)). After press left
						button, selection region is resizing by movement of cursor. Script function for
						resizing is execute on release mouse left button.
				</para>
				<para>
						For occurence that user doesn't want press left button, can before release button
						press <emphasis>Esc</emphasis> key. If <emphasis>Esc</emphasis> is press duration
						draging event with pressed left button, moving, resising or new selection is interrupt
						and select all object, which has been selected before pressing left button.
						If <emphasis>Esc</emphasis> is press and nothing mouse action is doing, all objects
						on the page will be unselected.
				</para>
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectAll;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectGraphicalOp;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectText;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_selectAnnotations;
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
				<title>Drawing and adding new objects</title>
				&gui_onclickFunctions_drawLine;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_drawRect;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_addText;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_strikeThrough;
				&gui_onclickFunctions_highlightingText;
		</sect2>
</sect1>
