<sect1 id="gui_menu_Tools" xreflabel="menu item Tools">
	<title>Tools</title>
	<para>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="gui/menuAndToolbarsFun/images/menu_tools.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Default menu item - Tools</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption><para>Default menu item <emphasis>Tools</emphasis></para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<title>Tools - description of items </title>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Options</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
                                        This menu item opens options dialog.
                                        (see <xref linkend="gui_settings"/>).
				</para>
				<para>
				        Script equivalent: <emphasis>options()</emphasis>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Insert pages from other document</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
                    This tool enables page insertion from arbitrary pdf document. 
                    After item selection a dialog is opened. This dialog works 
                    in 3 steps:
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Select pdf file from which we want to insert pages. When the file is 
                            selected, <emphasis>Open</emphasis> button should be 
                            pressed. Then the middle part is enabled and current top 
                            part is disabled (file can't be changed after Open is 
                            pressed).
                        </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Move pages which should be inserted from right item list 
                            into the left list in which are pages from current 
                            document. Use &lt;&lt; button to move currently selected
                            page from right list to left (before selected item in left
                            list). If you want't to move page back, use &gt;&gt; 
                            button. Inserted pages can be moved in left list by Up 
                            and down buttons.
                            <note>
                                Original pages (in left list) can not be moved or 
                                removed.
                            </note>
                            Items lists allows multiselection.
                        </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                                When all pages which we want to insert are in their 
                                correct position among pages from current document, press
                                OK button for insertion. You can press Cancel
                                button anytime to skip this dialog.
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="gui/menuAndToolbarsFun/images/insert_pages.png" format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
									<textobject>
										<phrase>Insert pages dialog</phrase>
									</textobject>
									<caption><para>Insert pages dialog</para></caption>
								</mediaobject>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>
					Script equivalent: <emphasis>mergeDocument()</emphasis>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Delinearize</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
                                        This tool converts linearized pdf files to normal pdf files. 
										When executed, a file open dialog is displayed. 
                                        Linearized pdf file should be selected. After open file
                                        is selected save dialog is opened for output (delinearized)
                                        file. After both files are selected, delinearization process 
                                        starts. This may fail if input file is not linearized or it 
                                        is not valid pdf document. In this case an error dialog is displayed.
				</para>
				<para>
				        Script equivalent: <emphasis>delinearize_gui()</emphasis>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>
</sect1>
