 <section id="required_libraries">
  <title>Required libraries</title>
  <para>
   These libraries are required to build and install PDF Editor:
   <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2"><tbody>
     <row><entry>qt3</entry><entry>Qt GUI Toolkit (Version 3.x)
      <note>
       Most linux distribution split libraries into two parts, binary (containing the library binaries) and development (containing headers and development tools).
       Also, in most linux distributions, the development libraries are not installed by default.
       For QT3 you will need the development version too. Name of the package is usually the same as name of the library binary package, suffixed by "-dev".
       (For example in ubuntu it is <filename>libq3-mt-dev</filename> for the development version, while the library binaries are named <filename>libq3-mt</filename>)
      </note> 
     </entry></row>
     <row><entry>boost</entry><entry>Boost C++ Libraries (smart_ptr)</entry></row>
     <row><entry>xlib</entry><entry>X Window System libraries</entry></row>
    </tbody></tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   Modified version of qsa library (Qt Script for Applications), version 1.1.5 is included in the source tree
   <note>
    If you have both Qt3 and Qt4 installed, you must have directory with Qt3 tools
    (<filename>qmake</filename>, etc...) before Qt4 in <envar>PATH</envar>.
     Pdf editor cannot be compiled with Qt Toolkit version 4.x.
   </note> 
  </para>
  <para>
   We tested compiling with various g++ versions - 3.x and 4.x were fine, it may compile on older versions
   like 2.95, but it was not tested.
   Program uses extensively RTTI, so the compiler used to build the program must support it.
  </para>
  <para>
   For building kernel tests, you need to have CPPunit installed
  </para>
  <para>
   For rebuilding documentation from DocBook .xml files, <command>gmake</command> (GNU make) is required
   and you also need:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For generating HTML : <command>xsltproc</command> from  libxslt and docbook stylesheets 
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For generating PDF : <command>xsltproc</command> from libxslt, docbook stylesheets
      and Apache FOP from http://xmlgraphics.apache.org/fop/
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   If some of the required dependencies is missing, documentation in appropriate format will not be generated.
   In distributed archive, HTML documentation is already generated.
  </para>
  <para>
   For rebuilding programmer reference, doxygen is required.
  </para>
 </section>
