<chapter id="page_space">
	<title>Page space</title>
	<para>
			The page space displayes one page from opened document. Page number is shown at the bottom of
			displayed page, as is number of pages in document. On the right  the actual position of mouse cursor
			on page in specified units is shown.
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="gui/images/pagespace.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Page space design</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption><para>Page space design</para></caption>
			</mediaobject>
	</para>

	<sect1 id="gui_pagespace_refresh" xreflabel="refreshing page">
			<title>Changing page information</title>
			<para>
					There are two independent information in page space which must be actualized.
			</para>
			<para>
					First is the image of the page itself and information about page count.
					This part is updated only if someone calls script function
					<emphasis>go()</emphasis> because it can be very slow (to update
					page after each change could be a performance problem).
					Reload page button in toolbars and menu (and many other useful
					functions) call <emphasis>go()</emphasis> automatically.
					But direct changes in <xref linkend="gui_objtreepropedit_id" />
					and changes using scripting do not update the page and page count automatically.
			</para>
			<para>
					The second is the mouse position on page. Position must be converted into 
					internal coordinates. The position does not depend on zoom level
					or actual rotation of page. (If the text starts at position
					[x:6, y:7 cm] in 100% zoom the same position will be used to started the text
					in 200% zoom.)
					<para>
							Notice: The most common way is to have the zero in the left-bottom edge of page and
							to have the maximum in right-top edge.
					</para>
					
			</para>
			<para>
					It can happen that after a zoom change the outer page space is not updated. 
					To corret this call either script <emphasis>go()</emphasis> function or click the 
					reload page button.
			</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="gui_pagespace_popupmenu" xreflabel="popup menu for page space">
			<title>Popup menu</title>
			<para>
					Right click of a mouse displayes a menu which will be displayed near the cursor.
					You can choose from two functions
					 <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
						<listitem><para><emphasis>Save page as image</emphasis></para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><emphasis>Save selected area as image</emphasis></para></listitem>
					  </itemizedlist>
					 The latter one can be used only when a selection is already present.
			</para>
			<para>
					Both functions store portion of viewed page to an image file.
					Format of the image file is depending on the system and version of Qt.
			</para>
			<para>
					<emphasis>Save page as image</emphasis> stores actual viewed page to an image file.
					If only a part of a page is displayed, only the part of page is stored.
			</para>
			<para>
					<emphasis>Save selected area as image</emphasis> stores only selected area.
					If selected area is fragmented or has not a rectangle shape, then a bounding
					rectangle of selected area is sotred. If selected area is bigger then actual displayed part of 
					page, storing
					area is cropped with same rectangle as page is cropped in <emphasis>Save page as image</emphasis>.
			</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
