<chapter>
	<title>Page space and what's all is shown</title>
	<para>
			In page space is shown 1 page from opened documents. In the bottom is shown which
			page is actual viewed, how many pages has documents and the right is cursor position
			on the page with units in which is shown position.

			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="gui/images/pagespace.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Page space design</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption><para>Page space design</para></caption>
			</mediaobject>
	</para>

	<sect1 id="gui_pagespace_refresh" xreflabel="refreshing page">
			<title>Refresh page and information</title>
			<para>
					In page space are 2 indenpendent parts, which must be refreshing.
			</para>
			<para>
					First is the page and information about count pages in the document.
					This part is refreshing only if someone call script function
					<emphasis>go()</emphasis>, because it's very slow operation (it's
					not very good refreshing page after each chage).
					Reload page button in toolbars and menu (and many others usefull
					functionality) are calling <emphasis>go()</emphasis>.
					But direct changes in <xref linkend="gui_objtreepropedit_id" />
					and changes via scripts are not automaticly projection to viewed page
					and information about count pages.
			</para>
			<para>
					Second is mouse position on page. This positions are converted to base
					internal page positions. This positions is not depending to viewed zoom,
					or actual rotation of page. (If user see that text is started at position
					[x:6, y:7 cm] in 100% zoom, than same position will be started this text
					in 200% zoom and rotated about 90 degrees.)
					<para>
							Notice: Usually is zero point in left-bottom edge of page and
							enlarge to right-top edge.
					</para>
					
			</para>
			<para>
					Sometimes after change zoom do not refresh outer page space. For correct view is needing
					refresh page type <emphasis>go()</emphasis> or click to reload page button.
			</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="gui_pagespace_popupmenu" xreflabel="popup menu for page space">
			<title>Popup menu</title>
			<para>
					If user click to viewed page with right mouse button, popup menu will be displayed.
					In this menu is at choice 1 or 2 items. First item is
					<emphasis>Save page as image</emphasis>. It's everytime to choose. Second is
					<emphasis>Save selected area as image</emphasis> which is to choose only if is
					some selected on the page.
			</para>
			<para>
					From names of items is clear that is using to storing viewed page to image file.
					Format of image files are depending on system and version of Qt.
			</para>
			<para>
					<emphasis>Save page as image</emphasis> store actual viewed page to image file.
					If is viewed only part of page, is storing only part of page which cantains viewed
					part (usualy is greate then viewed, but not whole page).
			</para>
			<para>
					<emphasis>Save selected area as image</emphasis> store only actual selected area.
					If selected area is fragmented or has not a rectangle shape, then is storing bounding
					rectangle of selected area. If selected area is greate then viewed part of page, storing
					area is cropped with same rectangle as is cropped page in <emphasis>Save page as image</emphasis>.
			</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
