<sect1 id="gui_settings_commandline" xreflabel="settings of command console">
	<title>Commandline tab</title>

	<para>
			The appereance of command editor can be customized in options dialog on tab "commandline".
			To execute options dialog click Tools/Options in menu or type <emphasis>options()</emphasis>
			in command editor or click the options icon in toolbar.
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="gui/images/options_commandline.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Commandline tab</phrase>
				</textobject>
			</mediaobject>
	</para>

	<sect2 id="show_retvalue">
		<title>Show return value of executed script in console</title>
		<para>
				If this setting is checked, command console will print return value of last command
				after executing it. It has basically the same effect as if last command was a
				parameter of function <function>print()</function>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="show_retvalue_complex">
		<title>Show return value also for complex type</title>
		<para>
				This will toggle displaying the return value for complex types, such as arrays,
				which are likely to produce lot of output, as arrays tend to be large.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="show_error_event">
		<title>Show errors from event handlers</title>
		<para>
				Check this if you want to see error from callback handlers.
				If there is error in callback handler which is called very often,
				like handler for current item in tree being changed, it can produce
				lot of output.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="show_cmdedit">
		<title>Show command editor</title>
		<para>
				If set, command editor is shown.
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="gui/images/command_options_cmdedit.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
					<textobject>
						<phrase>Command console without / with command editor</phrase>
					</textobject>
					<caption><para>Command console without / with command editor</para></caption>
				</mediaobject>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="show_cmdline">
		<title>Show command line</title>
		<para>
				If set, history is displayed in a combobox. This is useful when older history commands are needed.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="editable_cmdline">
		<title>Editable command line</title>
		<para>
				If set, editable command line is shown in history combobox.
				This is usefull when small space for typing command is needed.
				(set command editor	hidden).
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="history_option">
		<title>History option</title>
		<para>
				If set, history is saved and loaded to the command line. You can specify the maximum number 
				of lines to store.
		</para>
		<para>
				Note: History is saved when PDFedit's window is closed.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
