 <chapter id="callbacks">
  <title>Callback functions</title>
  <para>
   These are functions called from editor on certain events.
   Return value (if any) is ignored.
   If the callback function does not exist, it is skipped
  </para>
  <sect1 id="onChangeRevision">
   <title>onChangeRevision()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after active revision of document is changed
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onConsoleStart">
   <title>onConsoleStart()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called in commandline mode after calling all scripts specified
    in commanline parameters -
    unless some of the scripts exit the application prematurely, for example
    by calling <link linkend="exit">exit()</link>.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onEmptyFile">
   <title>onEmptyFile()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after the editor is opened without specifying any document on commandline (without opening any file)
    or if the current file is closed.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onLoad">
   <title>onLoad()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after document is opened
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onLoadUser">
   <title>onLoadUser()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after document is opened (after <link linkend="onLoad">onLoad()</link> is called)
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onLoadError">
   <title>onLoadError()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after an error occured while trying to load a document
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onPageChange">
   <title>onPageChange()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after changing to another page in the preview window.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onPageDelete">
   <title>onPageDelete()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after pressing "delete" key while in preview window
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onPageRightClick">
   <title>onPageRightClick()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after clicking with right mouse button in window with page preview.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onTreeLeftClick">
   <title>onTreeLeftClick()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after clicking with left mouse button on any item in tree window.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onTreeRightClick">
   <title>onTreeRightClick()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after clicking with right mouse button on any item in tree window.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onTreeMiddleClick">
   <title>onTreeMiddleClick()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after clicking with middle mouse button on any item in tree window.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onTreeDoubleClick">
   <title>onTreeDoubleClick()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after doubleclicking with left mouse button on any item in tree window.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onTreeSelectionChange">
   <title>onTreeSelectionChange()</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after selection in tree changes.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="onValueChange">
   <title>onValueChange(name)</title>
   <para>
    This function is called after some of special tools change its value because of interaction.
    Parameter is name of the special tool.
    Color selection tool calls this after user select some color in it,
    edit tool calls this after user presses enter or leaves the control,
    number tool calls this after user presses enter or selects some of predefined numbers,
    select tool calls this after changing the selection.
   </para>
  </sect1>
 </chapter>
