 <chapter id="cmdline_description">
  <title>PDF Editor Commandline parameters</title>
  <para>
   You can specify any number of filenames as parameters on commandline.
   One window will be opened for each file specified.
   If no file is specified on commandline, editor will be loaded initially empty.
  </para>
  <para>
   Name of files can be mixed with options (parameter that begin with a dash).
   Invalid option on commandline will cause editor to abort with error message.
   Names of options are case sensitive.
  </para>
  <para>
   Options which require a parameter can be specified in "short form", like <parameter>-d1</parameter>
   or "long form", like <parameter>-d 1</parameter>, both of these mean option <option>-d</option> with
   parameter <parameter>1</parameter>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Use <option>-script</option>, <option>-eval</option> and <option>-run</option>
   options to run any script besides the init script.
   These parameters are run/evaluated in the order they are specified on commandline
   and may be specified multiple times.
   If these parameters are specified in GUI mode,
   they are used in each window opened on program start, in commandline mode (console mode)
   they are used after commandline init script.
   After these scripts finish execution, the editor terminates.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="opt__help">
   <title>Option <option>--help</option></title>
   <para>
    Print brief help about commandline options to STDOUT and exit
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt__version">
   <title>Option <option>--version</option></title>
   <para>
    Print version of editor to STDOUT and exit
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt_d">
   <title>Option <option>-d (n)</option></title>
   <para>
    Set verbosity of debugging messages reported by editor.
    Only messages below or equal level specified in parameter will be shown, default is debugging level 1.
    Also, any of symbolic constants defined below (case insensitive), or starting part of them may be given instead of
    corresponding number.
   <table frame="none" id="table_debug_levels">
    <title>Explanation of debugging levels</title>
    <tgroup cols="3"><tbody>
     <row><entry>0</entry><entry>PANIC</entry><entry>Critical errors</entry></row>
     <row><entry>1</entry><entry>CRITICAL</entry><entry>Critical errors, but at least the program can exit somewhat gracefully</entry></row>
     <row><entry>2</entry><entry>ERROR</entry><entry>Usual errors</entry></row>
     <row><entry>3</entry><entry>WARNING</entry><entry>Comments about some unusual behavior</entry></row>
     <row><entry>4</entry><entry>INFO</entry><entry>Information about some internal behavior</entry></row>
     <row><entry>5</entry><entry>DEBUG</entry><entry>Debugging messages</entry></row>
    </tbody></tgroup>
   </table>
    Setting this to -1 mean no debug messages will be shown at all, not even the most critical ones.
    Debugging messages are sent to STDERR.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt_console">
   <title>Option <option>-console</option></title>
   <para>
    Run in commandline mode.
    No editor windows are opened and commandline init script is executed.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt_script">
   <title>Option <option>-script (filename)</option></title>
   <para>
    Run script with given filename.
    Look for the script in script path.
    If not found, look for the script in current directory.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt_run">
   <title>Option <option>-run (filename)</option></title>
   <para>
    Run script with given filename, but unlike <option>-script</option> option, script path is not searched.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt_eval">
   <title>Option <option>-eval (code)</option></title>
   <para>
    Evaluate given script code
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt_s">
   <title>Option <option>-s (filename)</option></title>
   <para>
    This is just shortcut for <option>-console -script (filename)</option>
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="opt__">
   <title>Option <option>--</option></title>
   <para>
    Stop processing options. Any further parameters after this one are treated as filenames.
    This can be useful if you want to open file, that have name beginning with a dash.
   </para>
  </sect1>
 </chapter>

