<!--  
	jmisutka (2006/08/11)
-->

<sect1 id="kernel_part_stateupdater_chapter">
        <title>Graphical state</title>
        <para>
		Content stream is a sequence of operations which alter graphical state. We
		need to obtain some information after each of these operations and xpdf code
		is no suitable for this sort of things.
		If appropriate functions are defined and the object is changed a bit, it could be used to display the content stream.
		It can be easily extended by adding appropriate operations when 

		Xpdf code is very difficult to extend here because it is adjusted just for
		displaying purposes. Again it has almost zero fault tolerance which was improved by adding
		some constraints into xpdf code.

		Functions altering the graphical state were heavily inspired by xpdf code. Most of the
		code is just copied from xpdf.
        </para>

		<sect2 id="obtaining_operator_info">
		<title>Obtaining information after every operator</title>
		<para>
		Each pdf operator has its function which alters the graphical state appropriately. The mechanism
		used by stateupdater is simple but very flexible. It gets a simple iterator which it uses to iterate
		through all operators. After performing a function assigned to the operator a functor with all
		needed information avaliable is called.		

		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
                          <imagedata fileref="kernel/images/stateupdater.png" format="PNG"/>
		  </imageobject>
		  <textobject><phrase>StateUpdater class</phrase></textobject>
		  <caption><para>StateUpdater class</para></caption>
		</mediaobject>
		</para>
		
			 <sect3 id="setting_operator_bounding_boxes">
			 <title>Setting operator bounding boxes</title>
			 <para>
			 Kernel supplies a special functor to the stateupdater, which gets called after every operation 
			 with infromation about the rectangle the operator used. The functor sets this rectangle as the 
			 bounding box of the operator.
			 </para>
			 </sect3>

		</sect2>
</sect1>

